A Guide to the William Newton Hale Papers 1951-1954
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
William Newton Hale Papers 1951-1954
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11646
ca. 3,925 items, contained in 10 Hollinger boxes, 1 oversize box, and 34 oversize folders.
This collection contains the drawings and business papers of Charlottesville architect William Newton Hale, Jr. (1920-1954), covering mainly the years 1951 through 1954. Hale's architectural practice was varied and ranged from small residential projects to large houses and commercial buildings in Charlottesville and the surrounding counties. He was a registered architect in the states of Virginia and North Carolina and a member of the American Institute of Architects.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to the Library by Lucy McIlwaine Hale, on May 30, 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born in Salem, Virginia, Hale moved to Charlottesville with his family when he was a teenager. He attended secondary school at St. James School in Hagerstown, Maryland, before receiving his B.S. degree in Architecture from the University of Virginia in 1943. After service in the U.S. Army Air Corps and a position with Snead & Company in Orange, Virginia, he moved to Charlottesville in 1945, where he became a designer in the office of architect Milton L. Grigg. Hale designed a number of commercial and residential projects while working at the firm between 1945 and 1951, when he left to open his own office.
As a child Hale was artistic and showed an early interest in architecture, particularly that of his native Virginia. In the late 1930s, while still a teenager, he began his architectural career by working summers on the restorations at Monticello and Shadwell. This early experience in historic preservation set the tone for much of his career. Even as a student he seemed to prefer traditional architecture, which predicted his later efforts as a restoration architect and designer of elegant custom homes in the Colonial Revival style. Yet his interest in early Virginia architecture extended beyond his professional practice: Among the projects left unfinished at his death was a book on the architectural history of the Petersburg-Appomattox, Virginia area.
Hale's promising career ended prematurely when he died suddenly on July 19, 1954.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains the drawings and business papers of Charlottesville architect William Newton Hale, Jr. (1920-1954), covering mainly the years 1951 through 1954. Hale's architectural practice was varied and ranged from small residential projects to large houses and commercial buildings in Charlottesville and the surrounding counties. He was a registered architect in the states of Virginia and North Carolina and a member of the American Institute of Architects.
Today Hale's residential work is probably the best known part of his practice, and many of his houses were published in William T. Stevens's book, Virginia House Tour (1962). Among the larger residential projects preserved in the collection are designs for Mr. and Mrs. Russell Alger at Farmington, Virginia and Mr. and Mrs. David Smith in Greenwood, Virginia. Numerous smaller residential designs include three houses for his family at 2022 Hessian Road, 1923 Meadowbrook Road, and 10 Deer Path Road, and one for his mother at 2029 Hessian Road, all in Charlottesville.
Working with investors Charles Barham and William T. Stevens, Hale helped to plan and develop the Bellair community west of Charlottesville. He designed seven to nine houses there and several more at the nearby Farmington Country Club. At the time of his death he was involved with Woodbury Ober in development of the Spicer Mill Farm subdivision in Orange County, Virginia, where he designed several of the initial houses.
Hale's most important commercial clients were local businessmen Charles Barham, M. A. Cushman, J. Deering Danielson, Donald G. Stevens, and William T. Stevens. His commercial projects include three motel designs: the Gallery Courts (now Budget Inn) on Emmet Street at University Avenue for Donald Stevens, the Commonwealth Courts on Ivy Road (Rte. 250) and a design for M. A. Cushman that was never built. Commonwealth Courts is now part of the University of Virginia's Kluge Children's Rehabilitation Center. Hale also designed a restaurant building for J. Deering Danielson that was built on Ivy Road only a few yards away from the Commonwealth Courts. It is now the University's Police Station and Information Center. In downtown Charlottesville he planned major alterations and additions to the Old Salvation Army building in the 300 block of West Main, a structure that was later demolished. Elsewhere, he designed a campus plan for Southern College in Petersburg, Virginia, which was not built.
While the drawings and papers come mainly from Hale's professional practice, the collection also contains materials from his years as an architecture student at the University of Virginia and a few samples of his early work. The student work is of interest because it shows that while Hale attended the University of Virginia in the early 1940s, its architecture program experienced a transition from the traditional "Beaux Arts" method of instruction based on study of classical buildings to one that taught principles of "modern" architecture. His student projects include watercolor studies of classical architecture, as well as designs for modern commercial and residential buildings.
Hale's talent as an artist was evident not only in his rich perspective renderings of designs proposed for clients, but also in his large murals at the Thomas Jefferson Inn on Emmet Street in Charlottesville (now the Federal Executive Institute). The murals, which still grace the walls of the Dining Room, depict Jefferson's two most famous works of architecture, Monticello and the University of Virginia.
While Hale's commercial projects were equally divided between the traditional and modern styles, his residential commissions were almost all traditional. This no doubt reflected his own interests as well as that of his clients. Most of his house designs fell into two categories: (1) the Palladian or Jeffersonian, which were formal, symmetrical, and classically detailed; and (2) the Virginia Piedmont vernacular, recognizable by their informal, asymmetrical, and accretive planning. Later work shows his awareness of popular contemporary styles, but even these had a formal quality; he rarely designed in such informal residential styles such as the ranch house.
Other Descriptive Data
Partial List of Buildings and Projects, 1951-1954
The following, in alphabetical order, is a partial list of the projects contained in the Hale Collection (11646, 11646- B).
Russell A. Alger Residence, Farmington
Box 1 / OS Folders 24, 25, 26; OS Folder 3 (11646-B)
1952-1954
Lee Armentrout Residence, 13 Old Farm Road, Bellair
Box 1 / OS Folder
1953
D. N. Baldwin Residence, alterations
Box 1 / OS Folder 33
1952-1953
Charles Barham Stores; alterations
Rose Hill Avenue, 500 E. Main
Box 1 /OS Folder 16
1952-1954
Charles Barham Residence
(Bellair #1, Rockstraw Residence, 19 Old Farm Road, Bellair)
Related project: Arthur Whitehill Residence
Box 1 /OS Folder 16
1953
Robert Carlyle Barritt Showcase
OS Folder 14
n.d.
Bel Air Houses (speculative)
[Camblos, F.G. Rockstraw]
Box 2
1953-1954
Bellair Mailboxes
OS Folder 7
n.d.
Bickers Residence, Stanardsville
OS Folder 11
1953
A.G. Bigelow House, 1717 Rugby Rd., addition
OS Folder 5 (11646-B)
n.d.
J. Fulton Bishop Residence, 6 Canterbury Road, Bellair
OS Folder 17
n.d.
Dr. A. Page Booker, 1873 Field Road; interior alterations
Box 2/ OS Folder 6
1951-1954
Brizzolara; 2 sheets
OS Folder 7
n.d.
William Brown Residence, alterations, Scottsville
Box 2 / OS Folder 17
1952-1953
Mrs. Joseph Carter Residence; Howard Drive; alterations
Box 2 /OS Folder 17
1952-1953
Orbin Carter Residence interior details
OS Folder 5 (11646-B)
1953
Ciglia Residence and Business
OS Folder 14
1953
Commonwealth Courts, Rte 250 (Ivy Road)
Box 4, Box 1 (11646-B) / OS Folder 27
1952-1954
Cooley, L. D
University Cafeteria (consulting project)
Box 2
1952- 1953
M. A. Cushman Residence, additions, Farmington
OS Folder 23
1951-1953
Cushman Business Buildings, retail and motel projects
Box 2 /OS Folder 23
1951-1952
J. Deering Danielson, Esso Service Station, Ivy Road
Box 2 / OS Folder 28
1951-1952
J. Deering Danielson Restaurant Building, Ivy Road
(now University Police Station and Visitors Center)
OS Folder 31
1951-1952
Donohue, L. F.
Box 3
1952
W. C. Dorsey Residence, alterations, Scottsville
Box 3 / OS Folder 7
1951, 1952
James Dunlap Residence; Bellair, Lot 12A
24 Canterbury Road, Bellair
OS Folder 7
n.d.
Elmwood Farm (Spicer Mill Farm Subdivision)
Box 3
1953-1954
Sam Estes, Stanardsville
Box 1 (11646-B)
n.d.
Farmington Country Club Additions
OS Folders 5, 31
n.d.
Gimbert & Wood, Apartment House (prospective)
Box 3
n.d.
Helen Hoy Greely
Box 3
1952-1954
Hale Residence #1, 2022 Hessian Road
OS Folder 7 (11646-B)
1946- 1947
McLennan Residence Alterations
(2022 Hessian Road)
OS Folder 7 (11646-B)
1954
Hale Residence #2, 1923 Meadowbrook Road
OS Folder 10, OS Folders 1, 5, 9 (11646-B)
1946-1947
Hale Residence #3, 10 Deer Path, Bellair
OS Folder 9 (11646-B)
1952- 1953
Mrs.Virginia Hale Residence, 2029 Hessian Road
OS Folder 6
n.d.
Mrs. Virginia Hale Residence (Amy Hale Holmes file)
2029 Hessian Road
Box 1 (11646-B) / OS Folder 9 (11646-B)
1951-1952
Mrs. Nancy Clay Hancock Servants House
2028 Barracks Road
Box 3 /OS Folder 21
1951-1952
J. T. Henley Residence, Crozet, alterations
OS Folder 14
1953
Mr. & Mrs. Neil Hevener Residence; 1 sheet
OS Folder 11
n.d.
Hillside House; 3 sheets
OS Folder 14
n.d.
James A. Holladay Residence, 34 Old Farm Road, Bellair
Box 3/ OS Folder 34
1954
J. S. Holloran Residence, alterations; "Tufton," Albemarle
Box 3/ OS Folder 34
1953
Holsinger Building Alterations
OS Folder 5 (11646-B)
1951
Ralph Horween Residence, alterations
"Merifields" Keswick
Box 3 / OS Folder 22
1952
Howard Johnson Restaurant alterations
Emmet St. at University Avenue
Box 3/ OS Folder 29, OS Folder 3 (11646-B)
1947, 1952-1953
Hudson, E. F.; Red Hills, Proffit, VA
Box 1 (11646-B) / OS Folder 6 (11646-B)
1951-1954
W. C. Hutchinson
Brookley Farm, Scottsville (Barn, entrance, etc.)
Box 4/ OS Folder 14
1952-1954
Arthur Latham Residence, alterations, Woodberry Forest
Box 4/ OS Folder 6
1952
Angus McDonald Residence, Rapidan, Virginia; 1 sheet
OS Folder 14
1945
Male Residence
OS Folder 33
n.d.
Marshall, Dr. V. H., Residence, St. Anne Road
Box 4/ OS Folder 21
1951-1953
C. P. Martin Plumbing Building; alterations
Box 4 / OS Folder 14
1951
Lawton Mahan Residence, Farmington
Box 4
1953
Ann Marvin-Louise Savage Residence
1518 Dairy Road, Albemarle
Box 5/ OS Folder 5 (11646-B)
1951-1952, 1954
Mrs. A. P. Mason Residence, Gordonsville
OS Folder 7
n.d.
Mrs. George D. Mayo, alterations; 705 Park St.
Box 4
1949- 1954
S. C. Miller Residence; 1 sheet
OS Folder 14
1952
H. R. Milliman Residence, Crozet; interior cabinetry
OS Folder 11
n.d.
Montaldo, Inc. sketches; 3 sheets
OS Folder 6
n.d.
Mount Olivet Church Alterations, Dyke, VA
Box 4/ OS Folder 29
1951- 1952
Unknown church add'n ("Sunday School Area")
OS Folder 3 (11646-B)
n.d.
James B. Murray Residence; alterations
Box 5/ OS Folder 11
1952-1953
Museum of Miniatures (Prospective)
OS Folder 4
1951
J. Robert Neal Residence; addn., 1923 Meadowbrook Rd
OS Folder 10, OS Folder 9 (11646-B)
1954
"The Nook" Restaurant, interior details
OS Folder 5
n.d.
Joseph Pace Residence, Bellair, 2 sheets
Box 5/ OS Folder 11
1952
"Perrywood", studies for entrance and wellhead
OS Folders 1, 3, 5 (11646-B)
n.d.
Daniel S. Poor Residence; alterations, Ivy, VA
Box 5/ OS Folder 14
1951-1954
Roanoke Rapids Hotel (Prospective)
Box 5
1953-1954
Rugbyside Association; sketch of site plan; 2 sheets
OS Folder 3
n.d.
Salvation Army Building, 300 W. Main, C'ville; alterations
Box 5/ OS Folders 12, 13
1951-1953
Haynes Settle Residence, Cherry Avenue
OS Folder 34
1954
R. G. Sketchley Residence (Unbuilt)
Lot 32, Blk. 4, Rugby Subdivision
OS Folder 31
1953- 1954
David Smith Residence, Greenwood
Box 6 / OS Folders 19, 20, OS Folder 3 (11646-B)
1952
Ruby Smith Residence, Alterations, North Garden, VA
Box 1 (11646-B) / OS Folder 6 (11646-B)
1952
Southern College, Petersburg VA
OS Folder 8 (11646-B)
n.d.
Spicer Mill Farm
Box 6
1954
Donald Stevens Residence, Cismont; alterations
Box 6 /OS Folders 7, 15
1951-1953
Gallery Courts (now Budget Inn)
"Stevens Motor Court," 140 Emmet St.
OS Folder 15
n.d.
Stonewall Jackson Memorial
Box 6
1953
"Spottswood Road" House (client unidentified)
OS Folder 11
n.d.
Thompson Residence
OS Folder 4
1947
H. B. Thomas Residence, Orange VA, 12 sheets
OS Folder 33
1951
Tremain Residence, alterations, Farmington
OS Folder 14
n.d.
Virginia Corporation (same as Ciglia Corporation?)
Preliminary Study for Laboratory
OS Folder 7
n.d.
John White, Barn Remodeling
Box 6 / Folder 5
1952
Dr. Arthur Whitehill Residence, Chapel Hill NC
Box 6 / OS Folder 22, OS Folder 3 (11646-B)
1952- 1954
George Worthington Res., Strong Point Rd. Stony Point,
Box 6 / OS Folder 6 (11646-B)
1950-1953
Worthington Cabin, Alterations
OS Folder 6 (11646-B)
n.d.
Unknown Projects
Perspective Sketches of Unknown Houses, 4 sheets
OS Folder 5
n.d.
Studies for Unknown House, 5 sheets
OS Folder 5
n.d.
Studies for Doctors Offices, 2 sheets
OS Folder 5
n.d.
Studies for Unknown House
(Same house in sketches in Folder 1 of "School Papers," Box 10), 5 sheets
OS Folder 5
n.d.
Unidentified House plan; 1 sheet
OS Folder 11
n.d.
Unidentified House plan; 1 sheet
OS Folder 11
n.d.
Plan for Unknown House w/ gambrel roof; 1 sheet
OS Folder 3 (11646-B)
n.d.
Yellow Frame house; perspective sketch; 1 sheet
OS Folder 3 (11646-B)
n.d.
Chippendale-style Highboy furniture; sketch; 1 sheet
OS Folder 3 (11646-B)
n.d.
5 sketch plans taped to 1 large white sheet
OS Folder 3 (11646-B)
n.d.
Addition for Unknown House; plan; 1 sheet
OS Folder 5 (11646-B)
n.d.
Unknown 2-story House, front elevation; 1 sheet
OS Folder 5 (11646-B)
n.d.
Unknown House; "View from the Southeast"; 1 sheet
OS Folder 5 (11646-B)
n.d.
Historic Preservation
Bremo, blueprint renderings (artist unknown); 4 sheets
OS Folder 3
n.d.
Corotoman, Weems, Virginia; site plan; 1 sheet
OS Folder 6
n.d.
"Windie Knowe"; measured drawings 2 sheets
OS Folder 18
1944
Gadsby's Tavern, Alexandria; "Detail of Tap and Bar" by Milton Grigg; 1 sheet
OS Folder 18
1933
Hollymead; "Detail of Dormers;" by Milton Grigg; 1 sheet
OS Folder 18
1940
Mrs. Nelson Brooks Residence; "Mantel Detail for Bedroom #1;" by Milton Grigg; 1 sheet
OS Folder 18
1940
Addresses of Existing Hale Projects
The following is a partial list of addresses for projects attributed to William Newton Hale. Most are from the years 1951 to 1954, the dates of the materials contained in the Collection, but some are from the period prior to 1951, when Mr. Hale worked in association with Milton Grigg.
Names are for original clients; current owners may be different. Key to Sources:
SPEC COL: Plans or other materials held by Special Collections
STEVENS: William T. Stevens, Virginia House Tour(1962)
LMH: Mrs. Lucy McIlwain Hale
BELLAIR, Charlottesville
Armentrout Residence, 13 Old Farm Road (SPEC COL, LMH)
Bishop Residence, 6 Canterbury Road (SPEC COL, LMH)
Dunlap Residence, 24 Canterbury Road (SPEC COL, LMH)
Guest Residence, 40 Old Farm Road (LMH)
Hale Residence #3, 10 Deer Path (SPEC COL, STEVENS, LMH)
Holladay Residence, 34 Old Farm Road (SPEC COL, STEVENS, LMH)
Richardson Residence, 28 Canterbury Road (STEVENS, LMH)
Reynolds Residence, 36 Old Farm Road (STEVENS, LMH)
Rockstraw Residence (Charles Barham House or Bellair House #1) 19 Old Farm Road
(SPEC COL, LMH) (Arthur Whitehill House a related project)
________ Residence, 41 Canterbury Road (LMH) (client unknown but identified by LMH)
FARMINGTON, Charlottesville
Alger Residence, 2 Lake Road (SPEC COL, LMH)
Cone Residence, 17 Farmington Drive (LMH)
Mahan Residence, 6 Farmington Drive (SPEC COL, STEVENS, LMH)
Tremain Residence, 5 Tennis Road (SPEC COL, STEVENS, LMH)
MEADOWBROOK HILLS/HESSIAN ROAD, Charlottesville
________ Residence, 1916 Blue Ridge Road (LMH) (client unknown but identified by LMH)
Barksdale Residence 1939 Blue Ridge Road (LMH)
Mrs. Virginia Hale Residence, 2029 Hessian Road (SPEC COL, LMH)
Hale Residence #1 (McLennan House), 2022 Hessian Road (SPEC COL, LMH)
Hashagen Residence, 2031 Hessian Road (LMH)
Kindred Residence, 2010 Hessian Road (LMH)
Vance Residence 2000 Hessian Road (LMH)
York Residence, 2018 Hessian Road (LMH)
Chadwick Residence, 2011 Spottswood Road (LMH)
Hale Residence #2 (Neal House) 1923 Meadowbrook Road (SPEC COL, LMH)
Marvin-Savage Residence, 1518 Dairy Road (SPEC COL, LMH)
EMMET STREET
Gallery Courts (now Budget Inn), client Donald G. Stevens, 140 Emmet Street (SPEC COL, LMH)
Howard Johnson Restaurant Alterations 100 Block of Emmet Street (SPEC COL, LMH)
IVY ROAD
Commonwealth Courts (now part of UVA Kluge Childrens Rehabilitation Center), for client William Barksdale, Jr., 2270 Ivy Road (SPEC COL, LMH)
Restaurant and Caterer's Shop (now University Police Station and Visitors Center), for J. Deering Danielson, 2304 Ivy Road, (SPEC COL, LMH)
Contents List
- Client Files
  - Mr. Russell A. Alger Residence, Farmington 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - Alger Residence 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Armentrout, Lee n.d. (Box 1)
  - Baldwin, D. N. 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Barham, Charles 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Bellair (constr.) 1954, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Bel Air Houses 1953-1954 (Box 2)
  - Bookstore Model Drawings 1945 (Box 2)
  - Booker, Dr. Page 1951-1954 (Box 2)
  - Brown, William 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Carter, Mrs. Joseph R. 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Miss Caroline Carter 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Cooley. L. D. 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - "Corotoman" n.d. (Box 2)
  - Cushman, M.A. - Apartment Hotel 1952 (Box 2)
  - Cushman, M.A. - Residence - "Farmoor," Farmington 1951-1953 (Box 2)
  - Cushman - Gentry Housing Crozet, Virginia 1951 (Box 2)
  - Danielson, J. D. 1951-1953 (Box 2)
  - Danielson Service Station 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Donohue, L. F. 1952 (Box 3)
  - W. C. Dorsey 1952 (Box 3)
  - Elmwood Farm 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - Helen Hoy Greely 1952-1954 (Box 3)
  - Hancock 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - Holladay, James A. 1954 (Box 3)
  - J. S. Holloran 1953 (Box 3)
  - Horween, Ralph 1952 (Box 3)
  - Howard Johnson Restaurant 1947, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
  - W. C. Hutchinson 1952-1954 (Box 4)
  - Latham, Arthur - Woodberry Forest 1952 (Box 4)
  - Marshall, Dr. V. H., Residence - Meadowbrook Heights 1951-1953 (Box 4)
  - C. P. Martin (Shop) 1951 (Box 4)
  - Mahan 1953 (Box 4)
  - Mrs. George D. Mayo 1949-1954 (Box 4)
  - Meadowbrook Road House 1946-1947 (Box 4)
  - Motor Court 1952-1954 (Box 4)
  - Mount Olivet Church 1951-1952 (Box 4)
  - Murray Construction Acct. 1953-1954 (Box 4)
  - James B. Murray 1952-1953 (Box 5)
  - Captain J. G. Pace 1952 (Box 5)
  - Mr. & Mrs. David S. Poor 1951-1954 (Box 5)
  - Promotional & Tentative 1954 (Box 5)
  - Roanoke Rapids Hotel 1953-1954 (Box 5)
  - Salvation Army 1953 (Box 5)
  - Savage, Miss Louise and Marvin, Mrs. Charles 1951-1952, 1954 (Box 5)
  - R. G. Sketchley 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - Small Jobs 1946, 1952-1954 (Box 6)
  - Mr. David Smith, Greenwood 1952 (Box 6)
  - Snead n.d. (Box 6)
  - Spicer Mill Farm 1954 (Box 6)
  - Mr. Donald Stevens - Alterations to Residence 1952-1953 (Box 6)
  - Stevens, William. T. 1951-1952 (Box 6)
  - Stonewall Jackson Memorial 1953 (Box 6)
  - White, John 1952 (Box 6)
  - Dr. Whitehill 1952-1954 (Box 6)
  - David Wood 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - Worthington, George, Jr., Edgemont - Strong Point Road 1950-1953 (Box 6)
- Office Files
  - Accounts Receivable Office '54 1954 (Box 7)
  - A.I.A. 1945, 1950-1953 (Box 7)
  - A.I.A. - 1954 1954 (Box 7)
  - Appointment Books (2), Telephone Numbers (1) 1952, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Bills Due 1954-1956 (Box 7)
  - Car Upkeep-Travel Expense 1953-1954 (Box 7)
  - Contract Forms 1954 (Box 7)
  - Contributions-Dues 1952-1954 (Box 7)
  - Employees Withholding Tax 1952 (Box 7)
  - Engineering Services 1952-1954 (Box 7)
  - File Labelled "Important - Miscellaneous Notes" 1953-1954 (Box 7)
  - Fire Regulations-Building Code n.d. (Box 7)
  - Licences - Professional 1952-1954 (Box 7)
  - Michael 1954-1955 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1945-1954 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts 1954 (Box 8)
  - Office Supplies and Equipment 1954 (Box 8)
  - Personnel 1951-1954 (Box 8)
  - Phone Calls 1954 (Box 8)
  - Printing # 1 1953-1954 (Box 8)
  - Printing # 2 1954 (Box 8)
  - Printing - 1952 1952 (Box 8)
  - Specifications n.d. (Box 8)
  - Supplies and Equipment 1951-1954 (Box 9)
  - Taxes and Insurance 1951-1953 (Box 9)
  - Time Books #1 n.d. (Box 9)
  - Time Books #2 n.d. (Box 9)
  - Travel Expenses 1952-1954 (Box 9)
  - Utilities - Rent 1951-1954 (Box 9)
  - Utilities 1952-1953 (Box 9)
  - School Papers # 1: Miscellaneous Sketches 1939-1943 (Box 10)
    Includes degree plan, archaeological field guide, book report.
  - School Papers # 2: Arch Construction B1, Fall 1940 1939-1943 (Box 10)
  - School Papers # 3: Arch Construction B1, Spring 1941 1939-1943 (Box 10)
  - School Papers # 4: Arch Construction B2, Fall 1941 1939-1943 (Box 10)
  - School Papers # 5: Arch Construction B2, Spring 1942 1939-1943 (Box 10)
  - School Papers # 6: Arch Construction B3 Fall 1942 1939-1943 (Box 10)
  - School Papers # 7: Arch Construction B3, Spring 1943 1939-1943 (Box 10)
  - School Papers # 8: History of Art B2, Spring 1942 1939-1943 (Box 10)
  - School Papers # 9: History of Art B3, Fall 1942 1939-1943 (Box 10)
  - School Papers # 10: Structures Problems 1939-1943 (Box 10)
- "Idea" Files
  - Magazine Clipping - Idea Files n.d. (Oversize S 67)
  - Magazine Clipping - Idea Files n.d. (Oversize S 67)
  - Magazine Clipping - Idea Files n.d. (Oversize S 67)
  - Magazine Clipping - Idea Files n.d. (Oversize S 67)
  - Magazine Clipping - Idea Files n.d. (Oversize S 67)
- Architectural Drawings
  - Drawing of Legislative Building; student work c. 1939, 1 sheet (Folder 1)
  - Charcoal Sketches; student work c. 1940, 39 sheets (Folder 2)
  - Bremo, blueprint renderings (artist unknown) n.d., 4 sheets (Folder 3)
  - Rugbyside Assocciation; sketch of site plan n.d., 2 sheets (Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous sketches from class notes file 1940-1943, 5 sheets (Folder 3)
  - Apartment House for Gimbert & Wood n.d., 2 sheets (Folder 3)
  - L. D. Cooley Bookscases n.d., 3 sheets (Folder 3)
  - Thompson Residence; sketch plans 1947, 13 sheets (Folder 4)
  - Museum of Miniatures 1951, 8 sheets (Folder 4)
  - Details for "The Nook" n.d., 2 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Studies for Fireplace Walls n.d., 4 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Sketches for Unknown House n.d., 3 sheets (Folder 5)
    Labelled "white" and "Ted Wood and White"
  - Perspective Sketches of Unknown Houses n.d., 4 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Site plan sketches for Marvin-Savage House n.d., 2 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Studies for Unknown House n.d., 5 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Studies for Doctors Offices n.d., 2 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Drawings for A.I.A. Exhibit (Alger, Smith, Hale, and unknown houses) n.d., 4 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Studies for Unknown House n.d., 5 sheets (Folder 5)
    (Same house in sketches in Folder 1 of "School Papers," Box 10.)
  - Sketch of Clubhouse, Farmington Country Club n.d., 1 sheet (Folder 5)
  - Montaldo, Inc. sketches n.d., 3 sheets (Folder 6)
  - Dr. A. P. Booker- Field Road; interior alterations n.d., 5 sheets (Folder 6)
  - Arthur Latham; interior alterations 1952, 5 sheets (Folder 6)
  - Mrs. William Newton Hale (architect's mother), 2029 Hessian Road 1952, 15 sheets (Folder 6)
  - Corotoman, Weems, Virginia; site plan n.d., 1 sheet (Folder 6)